Recently, I posted a story of health insurance on Instagram.
And my DMs were full of this one question.
Please suggest the best health insurance for my parents.
Honestly, this is one of the biggest financial insecurities for all the kids with aging parents.
Because medical expenses are increasing these days.
And there are so many wordings and terms and conditions in the insurance policy that you are not sure whether it will be useful or not.
So, in today's video, we will answer this question.
How to pick the best health insurance for your parents in 2025?
In this video, we will see the wordings of the policy, see the data and rank the companies.
Let's begin.
First things first.
Before understanding the details and terms of the policy, we have to see whether all these insurance companies make the life of their consumers easy or difficult when needed.
So, to understand the credibility of the insurer, we will understand these three metrics.
The first thing is complaints per 10,000 claims.
The smoother the claim process of a company, the less complaints will come.
This is the biggest indicator of how consumer-friendly an insurer is.
So, here I have the complaints data of all the insurance companies.
This is the average of the last 3 years.
To gauge the long-term performance of the company.
If the complaints volume of any company is more than 20, then that is tricky.
Anything less than 20 is really good.
Here, I can see the average complaint volume of Bajaj Allianz in the last 3 years is 3 per 10,000 claims.
That is really impressive.
HDFC Ergo has 8, United India has 9, ICICI Lombard has 11.
So, all these are really good numbers.
If I talk about the bottom, the worst numbers of Navi are 163 complaints per 10,000 claims.
After that, Star Health has 46 complaints per 10,000 claims.
There is a nuance here.
Navi's complaint number is very high.
But this doesn't mean that it is worse than Star.
Navi's total insurance business will be less than 100 crores.
Star's annual insurance business is more than 10,000 crores.
So, if the complaint data is so high on that scale, it means that the consumers are not very happy.
After the complaints data, we will look at the claim settlement ratio.
CSR tells how much percentage of all the claims in a year is settled by an insurer company.
The claim settlement ratio should be at least more than 90%.
If it is less than 90%, then it is still in a risky zone.
We have the data of the last 3 years.
HDFC Ergo has the highest claim settlement ratio.
98%, Digit has 97%, SBI General has 97%.
If I look at the overall, out of these 24 companies, only 7 companies have less than 90%. The rest are coming in the safe zone.
In this list, Navi comes in the bottom tier.
Shriram General comes in the top tier.
So, the claim settlement ratio of these 2 companies is the worst.
I would like to give a nuance in this.
Like other businesses, there are ups and downs in the insurance business too.
ICICI Lombard whose claim settlement ratio is 88.85% has reduced in recent times due to many reasons.
Because of which, it is not in the 90% threshold.
So, if you have ICICI Lombard or any top company's health insurance whose claim settlement ratio is less than 90%, it does not mean that your claim will definitely be rejected.
You should understand why this claim settlement ratio has reduced.
The third metric to understand the company's business is the Incurred Claims Ratio.
ICR tells us how much premium this company has collected in a year versus how much it has returned in claims.
This is the data of the Incurred Claims Ratio.
In the last 3 years, if they have collected 100 rupees premiums, instead of that, they have settled a claim of 115 rupees.
This is not sustainable at all.
In future, they will have to increase the premiums or they will be able to settle less claims.
So, the healthy range is 50-90% which are all companies in green.
This means that companies are able to keep their profits even after settling claims.
So, it is stable.
In future, if there are more claims in the next year, then they will be able to settle further claims with these profits.
So, 50-90% is the ideal range.
Now, if I add all the 3 metrics and give the final ranking, then in the top tier, HDFC Ergo, Bajaj Alliance, Tata AIG, these 3 companies have performed best in these 3 metrics.
The bottom results are not surprising.
Navi is in the last, then Star Health and then Shriram General.
The concerning thing is that Star Health's total revenue is more than other private insurers.
Still, their customers are not happy at all.
So, I hope Star Health improves its experience and service in future.
By the way, before moving on, if you want to buy health insurance for yourself or your parents and you are confused as to where to start, then you can book a free consultation call with my trusted experts and 1Assure. 1Assure is an insurance company backed
by Rainmatter by Zaroda.
In this consultation call, they will understand your needs and tell you which are the 2-3 best recommended policies for you. And if you have an existing health insurance policy, they will review it and tell you whether this policy is right or wrong for
you. Full disclosure, this is not a paid promotion.
I am not getting paid to say this or to say the name of any company.
But if you book a call from the links given in the description and if you buy a policy from 1Assure in future, then we will get a small commission at no extra cost to you.
So, if you like our work, this is a good way to support our channel.
There is a free call link in the description.
Book now and understand which is the best policy for your needs.
We have learned how to select a company, now let's select a good insurance policy.
In the world of insurance, remember one thing, the bad cuts out the good.
Even if your policy has thousands of good benefits, but if your policy has 2-3 red flags, then when you are hospitalized, you will have to take something out of your pocket.
So, the first thing is, you have to identify the red flags and avoid it in your policy.
The first red flag is so misunderstood, that people get to know about it only when they get a hospital bill.
Let me tell you a real-life story.
In Rajkot, a lady had a medical insurance of 5 lakhs.
But when she got a bill of 2.5 lakhs, out of that, she had to give 1 lakh to this lady from her pocket.
Why? Because there was a very big restriction in her policy.
It was written in her policy that the limit of room rent is up to 1% of the sum assured.
Meaning, she can't take an expensive room worth more than 5 lakhs.
The lady didn't like that room worth 5 lakhs.
She took a room worth 10 lakhs, thinking that whatever extra tariff is there, she will give it from her pocket.
5 lakhs per day.
But that's not how it works.
As your room type or room rent increases, then all your medical costs also increase proportionately.
Doctor's fees, surgeon charges, OT charges, x-ray, medicines, the fees of all these things can increase.
And whatever added costs are there, you will have to give it from your pocket.
This is such a big red flag.
Look at this policy.
The sum of 25 lakhs is insured.
Still, the limit of room rent is up to 10,000.
How is this fair?
You took such a big cover that you don't have to give it from your pocket.
But because of these restrictions, you will have to give a part of the hospital bill from your pocket.
There is another type of restriction in this, which is room type.
Look at this policy.
Covers hospitalization up to the annual sum insured.
Room rent covered for a single private AC room.
So, if that lady from Lajkot had this policy, and if she wanted a bigger room than a single private AC room, still, she would have to give a major part of the bill from her pocket.
So, whenever you are taking a policy, remember the first thing, no room rent or room type restriction.
Avoid this restriction straight away.
If you have this restriction in your policy, then either you put an add-on to get rid of this restriction, or you try to port your policy.
The second red flag, if you have a health insurance of 10 lakhs cover, does it mean that this 10 lakhs will be used in every hospital bill?
The answer is no.
And thanks to this bad red flag.
Look at this insurance policy.
It is clearly written that robotic surgery is capped at 1 lakh rupees.
So, even if you have a sum of 10 lakhs insured, still, the reimbursement of robotic surgery will be of 1 lakh only.
Rest, you will have to give from your pocket.
There are so many policies in the market, which already mention that even if you have a cover of 10 lakhs, but in all these diseases, you will get only this much from us.
This makes your insurance policy totally useless.
The name of this red flag is disease-wise sub-limits.
And whenever you are taking a policy, you have to make sure that there are no such conditions in your policy.
Now, there is another hidden trap in this, in which many insurance policies not only limit diseases, but also limit particular procedures and medical costs.
Look at this policy.
Surgeon, medical practitioner, consultant, specialist fees subject to a maximum of 25% of the sum insured.
Anesthesia, blood, oxygen, x-ray subject to a maximum of 55% of the sum insured. Remember one thing, the more the sub-limits, the more the complexity.
The more the complexity, the more difficult it will be to pass the claims.
This policy is of Star Insurance.
And after reading these terms and conditions,
I am not surprised that why people...
is happy with this insurance company.
The third red flag is co-payment and deductibles.
In the case of senior citizens, due to their pre-existing conditions or just due to their age, co-payment or deductibles become mandatory but it is very important to understand its impact.
Let's understand these two things one by one.
The first thing is deductibles.
Suppose in your policy, it is written that some insured 5 lakhs and deductibles 1 lakh.
This means that if you are hospitalized in the future, then you will pay the first 1 lakh of the hospital bill and after that the extra amount will be paid by the health insurance company. Suppose your bill is 3 lakhs, then you will pay the first 1 lakh
and the remaining 2 lakhs will be paid by the insurance company.
If your hospital bill is 40,000 rupees, then you will have to pay the entire 40,000 rupees in that case.
There are two types of deductibles.
One is the absolute deductible, which means that 1 lakh is paid once in a year.
And the second is the per-claim deductible, which means that whenever you claim, then you have to pay 1 lakh yourself.
So, if deductibles are compulsory for your parents, then make sure that it is a once-a-year deductible.
That you have to pay a total of 1 lakh at a time and not every time.
The second cost-sharing method is co-payment.
This means that every time there is a hospital bill, the policyholder has to pay a certain percentage of the bill and the rest will be covered by the health insurance company.
For example, if there is a 20% mandatory co-payment in your policy and the hospital bill is 3 lakhs, then you will have to pay 60,000 rupees from your pocket and the remaining amount will be paid by the health insurance company.
Again, like deductibles, many times co-payment is also mandatory for senior citizens.
But you should try to find a policy where there is no co-payment.
If we compare deductible and co-pay, then suppose you have a small deductible of 50,000 rupees and you have a bill of 5 lakhs, then you will have to pay 50,000 rupees.
If you have a bill of 10 lakhs, then you will have to pay 50,000 rupees.
But in the case of co-payment, as the hospital bill increases, your expense will also increase.
So in general, a small amount of deductible is way better than opting for co-payment.
But ideally, both should not be there.
We have discussed the red flags, now let's talk about the good things to have in your parents' insurance policy.
First things first, as our age increases, pre-existing conditions like diabetes, hypertension, asthma come.
And the waiting period for these pre-existing conditions is very long.
Many times, the insurance policy will say that these conditions will not be covered for 3-4 years.
So in this case, if you are taking an insurance policy and if your diabetic father has to be hospitalized for some diabetic issue, then that will not be covered for the first 4 years. This is very very bad.
So the smart thing to do is to look for a policy with a shorter waiting period.
Or the second option is to buy an add-on which will reduce the waiting period.
Look at this policy.
In this policy, there was a waiting period of 3 years for diabetes.
But by taking this instant cover add-on, you will get this cover from day 1.
Of course, the 30-day waiting period is for everyone.
So if you are buying a policy, no hospitalization expenses are covered in the first 30 days.
After that, such an add-on covers all your pre-existing conditions after the 30th day itself.
Second must have, always make sure that your parents' cover is very high.
Many children take a family floater insurance plan for their wife and parents.
There are two risks in this.
First risk, if you or your wife get hospitalized for any reason, then in the future, your parents who have a higher risk of getting hospitalized, will have less cover for them.
Second thing, if your parents get hospitalized and the cover is exhausted, then the whole family will not have health insurance for a long time.
So please don't think of saving premiums.
Take a separate health insurance for your parents.
The ideal setup should be that you buy a health insurance worth Rs. 10 lakhs.
If you want to buy more than that, then you can buy it.
But if the premiums are unaffordable, then you should take a policy which has an automatic restoration benefit.
This means that if the cover is exhausted after the hospital bill, then this policy will automatically fill your cover again.
Look at the wording of this policy.
The company shall instantly add 100% of the base sum insured under this benefit in the event of an admissible claim during the policy year due to which sum insured was partially or completely exhausted.
This means that even if you are using partially, still this insurance company will add Rs.
2 lakhs for you.
In many insurance policies, it also happens that until the entire sum insured is not exhausted, they will not restore.
Ideally, pick one which restores the cover even if it is partially used.
If these restoration benefit policies are not available, then the second option is to buy a super top-up.
Buy a sum insured worth Rs. 10 lakhs.
After that, buy a super top-up plan worth Rs. 20-30 lakhs.
As soon as your sum insured is exhausted, this super top-up plan will be activated.
And then the rest of the medical bill, the hospital bill, will be monitored by this super top-up plan.
You have to buy this super top-up insurance separately.
And it is very affordable.
If your parents are eligible for super top-up, then this is a great feature to have to increase your cover without paying an exorbitant amount in every year premiums.
The third green flag is very overlooked.
But in the case of senior citizens, it becomes mandatory.
It is home care treatment.
The reality is that being hospitalized every time along with the age is not feasible.
So many times doctors will also recommend to keep a round of chemotherapy or dialysis at home.
And in such cases, if there is no day care treatment in your insurance policy, then you will have to pay this bill from your pocket.
Or you will have to be hospitalized mandatorily for every treatment.
And that is an added burden when your parents are aging.
See this policy.
It is clearly written in this policy that we pay for chemotherapy taken at home.
We pay for dialysis taken at home.
And if the doctor is advising that the person should undergo treatment at home, then in that case also, the expense is borne by the insurance company.
In parents' insurance, domiciliary treatment and home care expenses should definitely be covered.
The fourth and last green flag is very personal.
But I swear by it.
After the age of 25, I feel that every person should get a full body checkup every 6 months or a year.
When I got my full body checkup done 2 years ago,
I realized that I have a non-alcoholic fatty liver.
And this is a disease that has no symptoms.
So if I had got this full body checkup done after 5 years, then the situation would have gotten even worse.
And in that case, I would have had to undergo major treatments.
After that one health checkup, my fitness journey started.
Thankfully, my fatty liver is over today.
And most of the lifestyle diseases are like this.
Symptomless for the first 5-10 years.
And when you start seeing symptoms, then it becomes very severe.
For which you will have to start a treatment or it is irreversible.
So please get a health checkup done regularly.
In the case of parents, it should be mandatory every 6 months.
My parents also get their full body checkup done regularly.
Now there are many such insurance policies, in which you get a free annual health checkup.
Now an annual health checkup, in which there is a full body checkup, that is of 4,000-5,000 rupees.
So if this service of 4,000-5,000 rupees is giving you an insurance policy, then your net premium is finally decreasing.
See this insurance policy.
All these tests are covered in this.
Complete blood count, urine routine, X-ray chest, vitamin test, lipid profile, thyroid functioning, liver functioning.
This entire package is covered in this insurance policy.
Means your 4,000-5,000 rupees have been reduced from the total policy amount.
Even if you are not claiming, still some earning is happening from this insurance policy.
Definitely take the free annual health checkup policy for your parents.
This was the last green flag.
Now I want you to pause the video for a second and take a screenshot.
Did you take the screenshot?
If you are going on a call with my team or any insurance company, then you have to ask all these questions properly.
And then understand which is the best health insurance for your parents or for you.
It will take 20-30 minutes in the call.
But please ask all these questions.
It is the question of your parents' future.
That's it for today, friends.
If you have not bought health insurance for your parents or for yourself, please buy it now.
You are taking a huge risk by saving premium money or by delaying it.
Thank you so much for watching this video.
I'll see you guys next time.